<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>predictive modeling on Gary Weissman, MD, MSHP</title>
    <link>/categories/predictive-modeling/</link>
    <description>Recent content in predictive modeling on Gary Weissman, MD, MSHP</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/predictive-modeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of bootstrapping approaches for identifying variance of predictive performance</title>
      <link>/post/comparison-of-bootstrapping-approaches-for-identifying-variance-of-predictive-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/comparison-of-bootstrapping-approaches-for-identifying-variance-of-predictive-performance/</guid>
      <description>Background Bootstrapping is a helpful technique for identifying the variance of an estimate in a given sample when no other data are available. In the case of the evaluation of clinical prediction models, bootstrapping can be used to estimate confidence intervals around performance metrics such as the Brier score, the c-statistic, and others. When the original model and its tuning parameters, and the original dataset are available, the data can be resampled and the model refit on each replicate to make predictions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the equivalence of different formulations of the scaled Brier score</title>
      <link>/post/evaluating-the-equivalence-of-different-formulations-of-the-scaled-brier-score/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/evaluating-the-equivalence-of-different-formulations-of-the-scaled-brier-score/</guid>
      <description>Background The Brier Score is a composite measure of discrimination and calibration for a prediction model. The Brier Score is defined as
\[ BS = \frac{1}{N} \sum (y_i - \hat y_i)^2, \]
where \(N\) is the number of observations, \(y_i\) is the observed outcome, either 0 or 1, and \(\hat y_i\) is the predicted probability for the \(i\)th observation. Let’s create an R function calculate the Brier Score:
brier_score &amp;lt;- function(obs, pred) { mean((obs - pred)^2) } The scaled Brier Score accounts for the event rate and provides an immediate comparison to an uninformative model that is equivalent to “just guess the event rate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>