<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>babelgraph on Gary Weissman, MD, MSHP</title>
    <link>/categories/babelgraph/</link>
    <description>Recent content in babelgraph on Gary Weissman, MD, MSHP</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/babelgraph/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Grey’s Anatomy Network of Sexual Relations</title>
      <link>/post/grey-s-anatomy-network-of-sexual-relations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/grey-s-anatomy-network-of-sexual-relations/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s the blog post originally posted on babelgraph.org on March 25, 2011. The relevant hyperlinks and igraph code have been updated to reflect the current state of things. The edgelist, despite many more intervening seasons, and thus many more romances, has not been updated. Here is a nice walkthrough of ERGMs based on this post &amp;ndash; sorry for the broken link, Ben.
This all began with an introductory presentation about social network analysis to a group of medical students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The structure of twitter participant relationships in conversations around #Libya, #Bieber, and #Rstats</title>
      <link>/post/the-structure-of-twitter-participant-relationships-in-conversations-around-libya-bieber-and-rstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-structure-of-twitter-participant-relationships-in-conversations-around-libya-bieber-and-rstats/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s the blog post originally posted on babelgraph.org on April 4, 2011. I suspect the twitter API and much of the code below are not up to date.
I am a recent comer to twitter, and it took me a few weeks to figure out what this was all about. Who are all these people tweeting each other and what do all these trending hashtags mean? Do these people all know each other?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the blog!</title>
      <link>/post/welcome-to-the-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/welcome-to-the-blog/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to this blog, which is the new home for thoughts and technical things. As babelgraph.org has been retired, you can still get the code at:
BabelGraph Alpha
Over time I will try to migrate the old blog posts (mostly dealing with network analyses and C++ using R) to here along with the very informative user comments, and updates.
For old time&amp;rsquo;s sake, here is the old thumbnail gallery from the BabelGraph Alpha release (mixed Linux and Mac screenshots).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R can write R code, too</title>
      <link>/post/r-can-write-r-code-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/r-can-write-r-code-too/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s the blog post originally posted on babelgraph.org on April 14, 2012.
In a recent blog post by CMastication, a little meme puzzle is presented with the introduction that a preschooler could solve it in 5-10 minutes, a programmer in an hour. I took the bait.
The original problem goes like this:
8809=6 7111=0 2172=0 6666=4 1111=0 3213=0 7662=2 9313=1 0000=4 2222=0 3333=0 5555=0 8193=3 8096=5 7777=0 9999=4 7756=1 6855=3 9881=5 5531=0 2581=?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rcpp is smoking fast for agent based models in data frames</title>
      <link>/post/rcpp-is-smoking-fast-for-agent-based-models-in-data-frames/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rcpp-is-smoking-fast-for-agent-based-models-in-data-frames/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s the blog post originally posted on babelgraph.org on July 11, 2012. Thanks to Hadley Wickham for referencing some of content here, and apologies for the broken URL. NB. The original C++ code didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to compile on my computer today. It required a small tweak with NumericVector::create &amp;ndash; see below.
In particular, R data frames provide a simple framework for representing large cohorts of agents in stochastic epidemiological models, such as those representing disease transmission.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>